we've been looking at the Advent of 18th
century empiricism
and I mentioned in passing that the
world in which we live today
is filled with people that have a
profound confidence in what can be known
through the senses it's the show me
generation if I can't taste the touch of
smells and so on then I'm not going to
believe that it exists and as I
mentioned
the disadvantage of empiricism
is that it rests so heavily on the
process of induction that can never
acquire an exhaustive amount of data
upon which to make final judgments that
it has a built-in limitation
with respect to philosophical certainty
and though when we look and stand back
and look at the 18th century reaction
against the speculative rationalists of
the 17th century
we have a tendency to think oh finally
science wins over all this rational
speculation and we're getting down to
Common Sense hardcore reality
so that we now can be confident in the
knowledge that we have what actually was
taking place in the 18th century with
this beginning of optimism of coming to
greater and greater certainty of truth
of the objective world was in many
respects a runaway train of skepticism
we will see fairly soon
that in fact what happened
in the 18th century with this runaway
train that it did end in complete
skepticism
so that at the end of the of the track
the question was being asked whether
science was possible at all
and this all has to do
with this simple little distinction I
looked at in our last session
between primary and secondary qualities
now Bishop Barkley
who I said was concerned
to leave room for God in the universe
and who sometimes is ridiculed in our
age as being extreme in his views of
things
is the one who
first really made popular an expression
that if you've never heard of Barkley
and never heard of his idealism or his
form of empiricism
you still would have heard this idea
when you were children in school the
question was posed before you
if a tree falls in the forest
and nobody is there to hear it fall
doesn't make any noise
does it make any sound did you hear that
poser when you're school man modern day
contemporary version of that is that if
a man speaks
in a room
and a woman is not there to hear him is
he still wrong that's that's the modern
version but you get the you get the
picture that if the tree falls in the
forest and no one is there to hear it is
there any sound
now the question that is inherent in
that simple poser
is the question is Sound a primary
quality
or a secondary quality
it sounds something that exists apart
from
someone's hearing it
or
is sound just as important upon the ear
as color is upon the eye
to be real
of course in modern days we measure
sound by physically measuring the
wavelengths that are there and we could
say that in all probability the
wavelengths would still be set in motion
by the falling of the tree whether
anybody's there to hear it or not but
we're not looking at this Through The
Eyes now of 20th century physicists
we're looking at it through the eyes and
the ears of 18th century philosophers
well it was Bishop Barkley who coined a
Latin phrase that has become important
in the history of philosophy
and that is the phrase Essie
asked
perkipi
SC s perkipi
which means in translation
to be
is to be
perceived
to be is to be perceived
so if you would say to Bishop Barkley is
there a sound in the forest
if there is no one there to hear the
tree fall
well he would answer that question
two different ways
on the one hand
he would say
that if there is absolutely no one
who perceives that tree falling
there would not be a sound
in fact there wouldn't even be a tree
if we take this principle to its fullest
conclusion
if to even be is to be perceived that
means that if it's not perceived
it doesn't exist not only the sound
would disappear but the tree would
disappear and if there were no one there
to perceive the forest the forest would
disappear
or to take it to its ultimate conclusion
not only the consequences of material
things would disappear
but matter itself would disappear
because matter itself is dependent upon
someone's perception for its very being
aha
we're saying that what this man is
concerned about
is to stop the tide of materialism and
to stop the tide of atheism now some
people assume that therefore what
Barclay was saying was that matter
doesn't exist at all
the tree doesn't exist the sound doesn't
exist you don't exist
nothing exists and everything is an
illusion
now there are those popular readers of
Barkley who have come to the conclusion
that this guy was just spinning out
nonsense and talking about everything is
an illusion no no no Barclay believed in
real trees
and Barkley believed in real sound
but he said there can't be
being without perception
remember I said that he would answer the
question
about the sound in the forest two
different ways on the one hand if you
would say to him if no one perceives the
sound would there be any sound he'd say
no
but on the other hand he would say
if you aren't there and I am not there
and nobody else in this world is there
to hear that sound there would still be
sound
because it would be heard by God
in this case in simple terms could be
called the Great
perceiver
by whose perception
reality holds together
and without his knowledge
the idea of things actually being in the
mind of God
nothing would possibly or could possibly
be
now he is not a rationalist with respect
to how we approach the external world
and that's why he's usually considered
one of the 18th century empiricists but
he's an empiricist of a very different
stripe
he's a throwback if you will to Clayton
to Plato
and to Augustine where reality
is ultimately
in the mind of God
because nothing can be
apart from God's idea of things
so if God would quit thinking about you
you would disappear if God would stop
thinking about trees in the forest they
would evaporate you see what he's doing
in an 18th century way is going back to
the biblical principle in him we live
and move and have
our being
so that unless God
is sustaining his creation
by his knowledge of the creation
the creation would pass out of existence
so what's going on here is
that he is trying to get away from any
view of matter or of the universe or of
the world that sees the world in
existing
independent from God
not only is the universe according to
Barclay dependent upon the work of God's
creation for its existence
but it is dependent upon God for its
Moment by moment continuity of existence
which is consistent with the classical
biblical doctrine of the Providence of
God that says that not only does God
create the world but by the power of his
own being he sustains the world and
without his sustaining it it would pass
out of existence
so now God is not just simply important
to science and important to reality
he's absolutely essential and necessary
to reality
so when he comes to the question of
defining truth remember to be is to be
perceived
you recall
that John Locke gave us the
correspondence theory of Truth
remember truth is defined by that which
corresponds to reality
now Barkley says
according to whose perception of reality
Locke said that all things
have
primary
and secondary qualities and the
secondary qualities are those ones added
by the perceiver
and are not inherent in the objective
world like the blueness in Roger's shirt
now it's that distinction in lock that
Barclay challenges
he says
that all qualities
of matter
are secondary
even extension itself
is a secondary quality
that requires a perceiver for it to be
and the problem that we have is that no
one has ever perceived matter
you perceive the qualities of matter
and we have deduced from these external
qualities that there is something
producing these external qualities and
those external qualities are produced by
this mysterious substratum that we call
matter
but what's the matter
with matter here if you're an empiricist
well remember
your perceptions are only limited to
outward appearances
and with our naked powers of perception
we never penetrate to the very essence
of things
we never get beyond the accidents of
Saint Thomas's substance and penetrate
to substance that is to say
we never have a direct perception of
essences
for a being
all that we know we know through
external stimuli external Sensations
external perceptions even the very idea
of extension is an idea that we have in
our minds as we observe something and we
see that it has shape and size and so on
texture
he would say that's secondary too
that's still external to the essence of
things itself in other words in simple
terms what he's simply doing here is
reminding us of the difference between
meta physics
and physics
through the senses the only realm we can
grasp is the Physical Realm
that which lies under it
or behind it or Beyond it is something
we never directly perceive
we don't perceive the essence of a thing
only the external qualities
from which we deduce or using locks
terminology abstract combine and relate
these ideas that we have that have been
given rise to by our perceptions of
these various qualities we see the blue
we see the material we see this shape
and the texture of a shirt and we come
up with an idea of shortness but
nobody's ever perceived shirtless
the senses cannot get
beyond the external realm of physics
to probe metaphysics and that's one of
the reasons in modern uh
theoretical thought people want to keep
the Departments of theology or
philosophy
distantly removed from science
and says science is restricted in its
theater or sphere of Investigation
back to what Plato said
to the phenomena
and what are the phenomena
the outward appearances of things
and even if you get a telescope that
magnifies your perceptive power of
distances a million times
or a microscope that magnifies your
perception of small things a million
times
you still haven't got beyond the realm
of perceptions
the perceptions are just that more
discreet
and more Discerning than what you had
before let me see if it's like stripping
off the levels or the layers of an onion
you know you strip off the top level and
you say oh there's more to this onion
than I saw before I strip the first
lighter off now I can see to the second
layer
but how do I know that the second layer
is there
the same way I knew the first layer was
there by perceiving it then I strip that
away or I get a more powerful microscope
that takes me dial to the third layer of
the onion
but I'm still
perceiving something it's just smaller
or deeper behind what I had seen
initially but there's no point at which
I get Beyond
my perceptions
and so that's what Barclays critique of
Locke was
he said all qualities in the file
analysis are secondary
and so in a sense he exploded this very
important distinction that Locke made
between primary and secondary causality
are qualities because Barkley is trying
to say
that we're Limited
simply to the external qualities
and if the essence is going to be there
and I can't perceive it
then either it isn't there and it's an
illusion
or somebody can perceive it
can perceive more than I can perceive
namely God
and so God the mind of God the
Transcendent being of God becomes a
philosophical necessity not only for
the existence of ideas
but for the existence of matter itself
for the existence of anything itself
there has to be a substratum but that
substratum we can't perceive
and if knowledge is all based upon sense
perception
then that drives us relentlessly to the
skepticism
that
we're left with if all we have are the
senses and the senses can't penetrate
essences
that all we have are appearances
and the scientists as well as the
philosopher is now rudely ushered right
back into the depths of Plato's Cave now
I said that for John Locke
the the definition of truth is truth is
that which corresponds to reality
but if you perceive reality reality
different from how I perceive reality
can there be such a thing as objective
reality
if what is real is dependent upon my
perception of it or your perception of
it and those perceptions are different
we can't really talk anymore about
objective reality we're now forced to
the subjectivism and relativism that is
so pervasive in our culture today
and so
Barkley makes a modification to the
correspondence theory of law
his definition of truth is truth is that
which corresponds to reality
as it is perceived by God
truth is that which is perceived which
corresponds to reality as it is
perceived by God remember I said God is
the Great perceiver
and his perception of reality is
absolutely perfect
because he is the author of it
he is the creator of it and everything
that is out there is a manifestation
of something that first is an idea in
the mind of God
and without God's understanding of it it
couldn't be at all
so do you see how this empiricist is
driving us back to a new kind of realism
that sees the physical world
as an extension
of God's Own thought
without which
it couldn't possibly be
so to try to construct
a science of the universe without God
according to Barclay is a Fool's errand
because without the god hypothesis all
science will end in illusion
and or skepticism
because science can never take us
to the level of Ultimate Reality and if
we can't get in the door of Ultimate
Reality we can't get to the level of
objective truth
and if you can't get to object of Truth
the only option
is subjectivism
and relativism
and skepticism
now as I said
Barkley jumps in the cab of the
skepticism of the earlier type of
empiricism and starts at going down the
track
and I said the Train's a runaway train
well it doesn't run away until Barclays
kept kicked out of the cabin
and the new engineer is David Hume
whom we might call the king of the
Skeptics it was hume's critique of his
predecessors that took empiricism to
what is called its graveyard
and brought a supreme crisis of
knowledge philosophical and scientific
when Hume was done the question was can
we know anything at all about anything
and that's what we'll take up in our
next lecture